Chelsea, Mass. First Congregational Church records, 1841-2012.
Congregational Library & Archives
Chelsea, Mass. First Congregational Church records, 1841-2012.
RG5514
Congregational Library & Archives
5.22 Cubic Feet
(6 boxes, 2 flat files)
The First Congregational Church in Chelsea began as the Winnisimmet Congregational Church in Chelsea, MA in 1841 with Rev. Isaac P. Langworthy as pastor. In 1851, the church split into the Broadway Congregational Church which renamed itself as the Central Congregational Church in 1871, and the Winnisimmet Congregational Church which built a new edifice on Chestnut St in 1852. In 1874, the Winnisimmet Church changed its name to the First Congregational Church and in 1877, a group split off to form the Third Congregational Church in Chelsea. In 1905, the First and Third Churches united to become the First Congregational Church in Chelsea and built a new building on County Rd in 1906. In 1946, the Central Church closed and remerged with First Church. After declining membership and funds in the 2000s, the church sold the County Rd building to the city of Chelsea, but the members of the church remain active in the community even without their own building. This collection depicts the administration, history, and activities of the First Congregational Church in Chelsea with the records containing programs, annual reports, financial records, member records, committee minutes and records, correspondence, pastoral records, photographs, pamphlets, ledgers, and blueprints.
First Congregational Church of Chelsea (Chelsea, Mass.)
Winnisimmet Congregational Church (Chelsea, Mass.)
Central Congregational Church (Chelsea, Mass.)
Plymouth Congregational Church (Chelsea, Mass.)
Third Congregational Church (Chelsea, Mass.)
Restrictions on access
Access to this collection is unrestricted and open to the public.The library reserves the right to restrict access to identifying information.
Acquisition Information
Materials were donated to the Congregational Library & Archives by the First Congregational Church in Chelsea, MA in July 2024; 2024-19.
Historical Note
The First Congregational Church in Chelsea, MA began as the Winnisimmet Congregational Church in 1841 with a sabbath school, ladies benevolent society, and ordination of its first pastor, Isaac P. Langworthy being organized in the same year. The church grew rapidly in its first decade to the point that it decided to colonize itself with Rev. Langworthy, a group of members, the church records, and the name moving to a new building in 1851 while the remaining members became the Broadway Congregational Church. The Broadway Church later changed its name to the Central Congregational Church in Chelsea, MA in 1871. The members that moved and remained as part of the Winnisimmet Church built the Chestnut St edifice in 1852 with the dedication in May 1852. In 1857, some members split from the church to form the Plymouth Congregational Church which only lasted until 1859. In 1858, the second pastor, Rev. Albert H. Plumb took over the pulpit from Rev. Langworthy. In 1874, the name of the church changed to First Congregational Church in Chelsea, but it was often still known colloquially as the Chestnut St church. In 1877, another group of members left to form the Third Congregational Church in Chelsea. However, changing populations and resources needed to support their respective congregations caused the First and Third Churches to work closely together after 1900 until they decided to officially unite in 1905 as one church under the name First Congregational Church in Chelsea with services continuing in Third Church's Reynolds Ave building. The last services in First Church's Chestnut St building were held in June 1905 before the building was sold. In 1906, the first pastor of the united church, Rev. Charles N. Thorp, was called and a new church was built on County Rd with a dedication in 1907 to accommodate the growing membership.
In 1946, the Central Congregational Church in Chelsea closed with many of its members and a large portion of its funds going to the First Congregational Church. In 1961, the church voted to join the United Church of Christ. As the 20th century continued, the church grew and changed according to the changes in the Chelsea community before seeing a decline in membership and funds in the beginning of the 21st century. In 2024, the church sold the County Rd building to the city of Chelsea for use by the school district. The current status of the church is ambiguous given the lack of building for regular services and activities, but the members remain active in the Chelsea community.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains records depicting the administration, history, and activities of the First Congregational Church in Chelsea, MA. The records include annual reports, programs, newsletters, manuals, directories, member transfers, committee minutes and records, Sunday school records, women's union records, correspondence, pastor and pastoral supply records, financial records, and legal records. The collection contains ledgers, photographs, posters, blueprints, pamphlets, member cards, and notebooks.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into four series with series 4: Administration and history, 1841-2012 being furthered arranged into three subseries. The series and subseries are arranged chronologically by start date.
Series 1: Auxiliary groups, 1841-2010
Series 2: Member records, 1859-1975
Series 3: Publications, 1878-1971
Series 4: Administration and history, 1841-2012
Subseries 1: Annual reports, 1874-1975
Subseries 2: Board and committee records, 1851-2002
Subseries 3: Pastoral relations, 1851-1971
Corporate minutes.; Church finance.; Photographs.; Women -- Religious life.; Programs; Church correspondence.; Clergy -- Appointment, call, and election.; Church management.; Church management--Handbooks, manuals, etc.; Soldiers -- Photographs; First Congregational Church of Chelsea (Chelsea, Mass.); Winnisimmet Congregational Church (Chelsea, Mass.); Central Congregational Church (Chelsea, Mass.); Broadway Congregational Church (Chelsea, Mass.); Plymouth Congregational Church (Chelsea, Mass.); Third Congregational Church (Chelsea, Mass.); Langworthy, Isaac P. (Isaac Pendleton), 1806-1888; Plumb, Albert H. (Albert Hale) (1829-1907); Houghton, Ross C.; Sahakian, William S.
- Auxiliary groups, 1841 2010; 1841-2010
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains records from the various groups and organizations at First Congregational Church including the women's union, sabbath school, christian endeavor, and mother's club. The records include annual reports, minutes, member lists, record books, and other documents.
  - Ladies benevolent society annual reports, minutes, and members, 1841 1852; 1841-1852 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Sabbath school annual reports and minutes, 1878 1900; 1878-1900 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Church school miscellaneous, 1907 1949; 1907-1949 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Christian endeavor society members and minutes, 1938 1951; 1938-1951 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Mother's club minutes, 1958 1977; 1958-1977 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Church school superintendent resignation, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Mother's club minutes, 1977 1980; 1977-1980 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Winnisimmet union minutes, 1979 1991; 1979-1991 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Winnisimmet union minutes, 1991 2010; 1991-2010 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Winnisimmet union church fair planning, 2001 2008; 2001-2008 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Member records, 1859 1975; 1859-1975
  This series includes vital statistics for the members of First Congregational Church including member cards, membership transfers, baptisms, and addresses.
  - Member transfers, 1859 1949; 1859-1949 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Former member cards, 1905 1965; 1905-1965 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Member transfers, 1909 1975; 1909-1975 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Address list, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Baptism records, 1912 1942; 1912-1942 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Member records, 1917 1973; 1917-1973 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Baptisms by Rev. Hickox, 1942 1947; 1942-1947 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Publications, 1878 1971; 1878-1971
  This series includes records published by or for the church including manuals, directory and annual record pamphlets, programs, newsletters, and event cards.
  - Winnisimmet church annual record and directory pamphlets, 1872 1874; 1872-1874 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Annual record and directory pamphlets, 1874 1900; 1874-1900 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - First and third church manuals, 1878 1912; 1878-1912 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Third church bulletins and event cards, 1885 1905; 1885-1905 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Central church annual record and directory pamphlet, 1898 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Third church directory, 1905 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Programs, 1906 1908; 1906-1908 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Programs, 1909 1910; 1909-1910 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Programs, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Programs, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Programs, 1913 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Programs, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Programs, 1915 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Programs, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Programs, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Programs, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Programs, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Programs, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Programs, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Programs, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Programs, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Programs, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Programs, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Programs, 1926 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Programs, 1927 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Programs, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Programs, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Programs, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Programs, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Programs, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Programs, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Programs, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Programs, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Programs, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Programs, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Programs, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Programs, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Programs, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Programs, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Programs, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Programs, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Programs, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Programs, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Programs, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Programs, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Programs, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Programs, 1949 1951; 1949-1951 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Programs, 1955 1971; 1955-1971 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Newsletters, 1956 1961; 1956-1961 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Administration and history, 1841 2012; 1841-2012
  This series contains records relating to the administration and history of the church including annual reports, pastoral relations, and the church's administrative boards and committees. The records include reports, minutes, correspondence, invitaions, resumes, record books, sermons, photos, posters and wall hangings, honor rolls, plans, financial records, legal records, histories, yearbook reports, anniversary records, military service photos from WWII, treasurer's and clerk's records, and publicity.
  - Annual reports, 1874 1975; 1874-1975
    This subseries contains handwritten and printed annual reports from various groups and persons within the church presented at the annual meeting.
    - Annual reports, 1874 1878; 1874-1878 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Annual reports, 1909 1910; 1909-1910 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Annual reports, 1910 1911; 1910-1911 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Annual reports, 1911 1912; 1911-1912 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Annual reports, 1912 1913; 1912-1913 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Annual reports, 1913 1914; 1913-1914 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Annual reports, 1914 1915; 1914-1915 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Annual reports, 1915 1916; 1915-1916 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Annual reports, 1916 1917; 1916-1917 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Annual reports, 1917 1918; 1917-1918 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Annual reports, 1918 1919; 1918-1919 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Annual reports, 1919 1920; 1919-1920 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Annual reports, 1920 1921; 1920-1921 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Annual reports, 1921 1922; 1921-1922 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Annual reports, 1922 1923; 1922-1923 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Annual reports, 1923 1924; 1923-1924 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Annual reports, 1924 1925; 1924-1925 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Annual reports, 1925 1929; 1925-1929 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Annual reports, 1926 1927; 1926-1927 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Annual reports, 1929 1930; 1929-1930 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Annual reports, 1930 1931; 1930-1931 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Annual reports, 1931 1932; 1931-1932 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Annual reports, 1932 1933; 1932-1933 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Annual reports, 1933 1934; 1933-1934 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Annual reports, 1934 1935; 1934-1935 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Annual reports, 1935 1936; 1935-1936 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Annual reports, 1936 1937; 1936-1937 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Annual reports, 1937 1938; 1937-1938 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Annual reports, 1938 1939; 1938-1939 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Annual reports, 1939 1940; 1939-1940 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Annual reports, 1940 1941; 1940-1941 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Annual reports, 1941 1942; 1941-1942 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Annual reports, 1942 1943; 1942-1943 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Annual reports, 1943 1944; 1943-1944 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Annual reports, 1944 1945; 1944-1945 (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Annual reports, 1945 1946; 1945-1946 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Annual reports, 1946 1947; 1946-1947 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Annual reports, 1947 1948; 1947-1948 (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Annual reports, 1948 1949; 1948-1949 (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - Annual reports, 1952 1954; 1952-1954 (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - Annual reports, 1954 1955; 1954-1955 (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - Annual reports, 1955 1956; 1955-1956 (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - Annual reports, 1956 1957; 1956-1957 (Box 2, Folder 53)
    - Annual reports, 1957 1958; 1957-1958 (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - Annual reports, 1958 1959; 1958-1959 (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - Annual reports, 1959 1960; 1959-1960 (Box 2, Folder 56)
    - Annual reports, 1960 1961; 1960-1961 (Box 2, Folder 57)
    - Annual reports, 1961 1962; 1961-1962 (Box 2, Folder 58)
    - Annual reports, 1962 1963; 1962-1963 (Box 2, Folder 59)
    - Annual reports, 1963 1964; 1963-1964 (Box 2, Folder 60)
    - Annual reports, 1964 1965; 1964-1965 (Box 2, Folder 61)
    - Annual reports, 1965 1966; 1965-1966 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Annual reports, 1966 1975; 1966-1975 (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Board and committee records, 1851 2002; 1851-2002
    This subseries contains records from various boards and committees within the church including the advisory board, prudential committee which was renamed the trustees in 1969, the board of deacons, the building committee, the church committee, and the finance committeee. The records include minutes, reports, correspondence, record books, and other related documents.
    - Building committee minutes, 1851 (Box 2, Folder 63)
    - Third church church committee, 1887 1898; 1887-1898 (Box 2, Folder 64)
    - Advisory board minutes, 1889 1891; 1889-1891 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Deacons' minutes and records, 1897 1911; 1897-1911 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Advisory board minutes, 1899 1901; 1899-1901 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Prudential committee minutes, 1901 1920; 1901-1920 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Deacons' election and terms, 1905 1911; 1905-1911 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Prudential committee minutes, 1914 1938; 1914-1938 (Box 5, Folder 7)
      Separated Materials
      Records were removed from this folder and placed into Prudential committee records, 1915-1937 for preservation purposes.
    - Prudential committee records, 1915 1937; 1915-1937 (Box 3, Folder 6)
      These records were removed from Prudendial committee minutes, 1914-1938 for preservation purposes.
    - Prudential committee minutes, 1926 1953; 1926-1953 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Trustees' annual fund reports, 1932 2000; 1932-2000 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Prudential committee reports, minutes, and correspondence, 1940 1953; 1940-1953 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Advisory board minutes, 1951 1957; 1951-1957 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Trustees' minutes, 1953 1982; 1953-1982 (Box 3, Folder 11-12)
    - Finance committee appeals and offerings, 1965 1968; 1965-1968 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Finance committee appeals and offerings, 1968 1984; 1968-1984 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Trustees' minutes, 1982 2002; 1982-2002 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Pastoral relations, 1851 1971; 1851-1971
    This subseries contains records related to the pastors of the church, the pastoral supply committee, and the ecclesiastical councils involving the pastors. The records include correspondence, resumes, invitations, reports, sermons, and other documents.
    - Ecclesiastical councils, 1851 1919; 1851-1919 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Rev. Isaac Langworthy, 1858 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Rev. Albert Plumb, 1858 1865; 1858-1865 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Rev. A. J. Titsworth, 1878 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Rev. Ross Houghton, 1901 1902; 1901-1902 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Rev. Charles Thorp, 1912 1920; 1912-1920 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Rev. John Hastings Quint, 1913 1942; 1913-1942 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Pastor candidate resumes, 1937 1942; 1937-1942 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Rev. Edward Hickox, 1942 1947; 1942-1947 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Pastoral supply report and correspondence, 1942 1948; 1942-1948 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Rev. William Rowlands, 1948 1955; 1948-1955 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Rev. Rowlands' sermon, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Rev. William Sahakian, 1955 1958; 1955-1958 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Rev. Gerald Ciarcia, 1958 1963; 1958-1963 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Rev. Harold Woodbury, 1970 1971; 1970-1971 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Building photos, undated (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Church maintenance and keys, undated (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Member photos, undated (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Record of quartettes, undated (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Reports, undated (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Winnisimmet chapel dedication, 1841 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 1847 1942; 1847-1942 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Washington Ave naming, 1850 1907; 1850-1907 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Church history, 1852 1908; 1852-1908 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Plymouth church organization and installation, 1857 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence, 1876 1971; 1876-1971 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Third church letters and financial records, 1878 1905; 1878-1905 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Building photos, 1878 1908; 1878-1908 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Central church organization, 1892 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Third church clerk's records, 1894 1902; 1894-1902 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Third church budgets, 1897 1903; 1897-1903 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Special event display, 1905 1941; 1905-1941 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Building renovation and maintenance, 1906 1943; 1906-1943 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Pledges and financial records, 1907 1944; 1907-1944 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Photos and honor roll, 1908 1929; 1908-1929 (Folder 2)
  - Photos and plans, 1958 1960; 1908-1960 (Folder 8)
  - Central church's treasurer's book, 1909 1931; 1909-1931 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Government correspondence, 1910 1943; 1910-1943 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Yearbook reports, 1911 1950; 1911-1950 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Church minutes, 1912 1955; 1912-1955 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Estates, legacies, and restricted funds, 1914 1961; 1914-1961 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Property committee rules and janitor duties, 1928 1955; 1928-1955 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Brotherhood photo, 1930 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Treasurer's reports, 1931 1973; 1931-1973 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Library record, 1933 1949; 1933-1949 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Treasurer's correspondence and records, 1935 1950; 1935-1950 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Military service photos, 1940 1949; circa 1940s (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Budget, 1940 1974; 1940-1974 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - 100th anniversary, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Officer ballots, 1942 1947; 1942-1947 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Central church fund disposition, 1946 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Minnie Chapin appreciation, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Plans, 1951 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Church minutes, 1955 1982; 1955-1982 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - 50th anniversary rededication, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Alumni banquet photos and labels, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Publicity, 1962 1969; 1962-1969 (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - By-laws, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - Yearbook report and preparation, 1970 1971; 1970-1971 (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - Financial correspondence, 1972 1973; 1972-1973 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Financial documents, 1975 1995; 1975-1995 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - 75th anniversary, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - Church minutes and reports, 1982 2012; 1982-2012 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - 150th anniversary, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - Financial documents, 1991 1994; 1991-1994 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Financial documents, 1993 1996; 1993-1996 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Financial documents, 1993 2001; 1993-2001 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Financial documents, 1995 1997; 1995-1997 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Financial documents, 1996 1998; 1996-1998 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Financial documents, 1998 2000; 1998-2000 (Box 4, Folder 34)